<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: PAG | PAG, IIT Roorkee]]></title>
  <link href="http://pag.sdslabs.co/blog//blog/categories/pag/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://pag.sdslabs.co/blog//"/>
  <updated>2014-08-14T19:24:47+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://pag.sdslabs.co/blog//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Programming & Algorithms Group, Software Development Section, IIT Roorkee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interview: ACM ICPC World Finalist]]></title>
    <link href="http://pag.sdslabs.co/blog//2014/05/17/interview-acm-icpc-world-finalist/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-17T00:15:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://pag.sdslabs.co/blog//2014/05/17/interview-acm-icpc-world-finalist</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This year we have our team 3Spades contesting in the ACM ICPC World Finals’ 14. Last year, IIT Roorkee was proud to having been represented by the team 65th bit comprising of Sharat Ibrahimpur, Tarun Goyal and Dipit Grover. Their team eventually finished 60th, and the first among all Indian teams for that year. We present to you an interview of Sharat Ibrahimpur as he speaks to PAG about what got him interested in competitive programming, where did he get his motivation from, what does it take to become a good programmer and about what students in general should focus on in college. </p>

<h3 id="when-and-how-were-you-introduced-to-programming">When and how were you introduced to programming?</h3>

<p>I was introduced to competitive programming during the end of my third year at Roorkee. Before that for almost an year I was actively solving problems posted on projecteuler.net which gave me a stronghold on math based problems. I was introduced to Project Euler by one of my department seniors while CodeChef was a random accident on the internet. </p>

<h3 id="what-is-the-secret-to-becoming-a-good-programmer">What is the secret to becoming a good programmer?</h3>

<p>The secret to becoming a good programmer is to have a basic understanding of algorithms in almost all the areas. Have a good understanding of few and try to be a master in one. This is pretty feasible. </p>

<h3 id="how-did-you-guys-come-together">How did you guys come together?</h3>

<p>All three of us competed from different teams during 2011-12. Tarun’s team had performed exceptionally well and I heard from many people about Dipit’s problem solving skills. All that was left on my part was to convince these guys to team up with me. They said yes and rest as you know is history :P</p>

<h3 id="when-did-you-start-taking-it-seriously-to-the-extent-of-preparing-for-icpc">When did you start taking it seriously to the extent of preparing for ICPC?</h3>

<p>I started aspiring to perform well in ICPC at the beginning of my fourth year. Though serious preparations began when I failed to perform well in the Kanpur online round during my first attempt. Its good to take failures to your heart when you know you have another attempt left. </p>

<h3 id="who-is-your-inspirationmotivationrole-model">Who is your Inspiration/Motivation/role-model?</h3>

<p>Inspiration? No one in particular. I was motivated by the fact that the best minds across the world will be taking part in this contest. What better way than this to challenge your problem solving skills. 
I have always looked up to the performance of team proof from IIT Delhi. Their team has been a role model to me. </p>

<h3 id="how-much-does-software-engineering-involves-algorithmic-problem-solving">How much does software engineering involves algorithmic problem-solving?</h3>

<p>If you ask me how many problems, that we solve on a day to day basis, are as fancy as the problems you see in the contests then the answer is none. But, if you ask me if algorithmic problem solving skills help in delivering better solutions in your job then the answer is yes.</p>

<h3 id="did-your-deep-interest-in-algorithms-have-any-side-effects-too-like-maybe-affecting-your-cgpa">Did your deep interest in algorithms have any side effects too? Like maybe affecting your CGPA?</h3>

<p>Yup it does have many side effects. CGPA is the one thing that took the hardest blow in my case. During my final exams I had on one hand the choice of studying courses that I didn’t like and on the other I had the option of solving interesting problems. My brain would always convince me to pick the latter. Other things that got affected is the amount of time I spent on arbit things like watching TV series or bakar with friends. You can’t really help it. Everyone gets 24 hours a day. Neither a minute less nor a minute more.</p>

<h3 id="what-are-your-plans-for-the-future">What are your plans for the future?</h3>

<p>The learning curve at Goldman has been a steep one till now. Hoping to gain more work experience from this job. </p>

<h3 id="any-piece-of-advice-for-the-students">Any piece of advice for the students?</h3>

<p>Learn as many skills as you can now. This is the time when the day is all yours as you are not being paid to deliver something. Challenge yourself by doing something productive for long hours every day and then take a break from it to relax. The satisfaction is immense. 
On a side note, many of you might think spending time on quora or reading blogs is better than Facebook as it gives you a feeling that you have gained some precious knowledge. But let me tell you, any piece of knowledge that has not been put to good use is garbage. So don’t acquire knowledge at a pace faster than at which you use it.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/Interview/WF.jpg"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Codematics 2k14]]></title>
    <link href="http://pag.sdslabs.co/blog//2014/04/05/codematics-2k14/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-05T19:23:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://pag.sdslabs.co/blog//2014/04/05/codematics-2k14</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On the 8th of March 2014, PAG organised an online Maths contest along the lines of Project Euler, <a href="http://erdos.sdslabs.co/">Codematics</a>, as part of the annual Hobbies club fest of IIT Roorkee, Shrishti. It was a 24 hour long competition (March 8 21:00 to March 9 21:00 IST) and was targeted at all the Maths enthusiasts of the IITR campus and the world. The contest had 24 questions - ranging from cakewalk to tricky - that challenged the participants. There was no negative scoring and everyone could make unlimited attempts for each question.</p>

<p>The questions in the contest were based on a variety of concepts from number theory, combinatorics, geometry and some general aptitude and puzzles. And what’s more, we had an overwhelming response. There were more than 100 participants and over 1600 submissions. It was a close contest with three of the participants, Sukun Tarachandani, Priyanshu Seth and Yashpal Choudhary (all from IITR) solving as many as 16 questions, the highest. But the first one to solve them, Sukun Tarachandani was declared the winner of Codematics 2014.</p>

<p>This year the special thing about Codematics was that it was hosted on a new platform, <a href="http://erdos.sdslabs.co/">Erdős</a>. It is an application for math geeks to try out new mathematical problems and keep track of who solves what. The design of Erdős is clean and card-based, with a focus on user-interaction above everything else. This web portal is maintained by <a href="https://www.facebook.com/SDSLabs">SDSLabs</a>.</p>

<p>We tried our best to make the contest perfect for you guys, however there were small glitches or misunderstandings in some questions, which were soon fixed. We are sorry for that. Hope you enjoyed giving this competition and we would like to say that we enjoyed even more, putting it up for you. We’ll be back next year with another Codematics and in the meantime we will host more contests on Erdos. </p>

<p>You can still attempt the codematics problems <a href="http://erdos.sdslabs.co/">here</a>. We would love to hear from you. Just drop us a mail at <a href="&#109;&#097;&#105;&#108;&#116;&#111;:&#112;&#097;&#103;&#105;&#105;&#116;&#114;&#064;&#103;&#109;&#097;&#105;&#108;&#046;&#099;&#111;&#109;">&#112;&#097;&#103;&#105;&#105;&#116;&#114;&#064;&#103;&#109;&#097;&#105;&#108;&#046;&#099;&#111;&#109;</a>.</p>

<p><em>Team Codematics</em>: 
<img src="/images/posts/Codematics/2k14.jpg"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Insomnia 2k14]]></title>
    <link href="http://pag.sdslabs.co/blog//2014/03/27/insomnia-2k14/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-27T14:44:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://pag.sdslabs.co/blog//2014/03/27/insomnia-2k14</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It has been a busy month for PAG. We have been organizing several contests on the IIT Roorkee intranet as well as online related to programming and general aptitude prowess. But it was the 15th of March that saw the occurrence of most awaited event organized by the group- Insomnia! This was the 5th edition of the annual international programming contest organized by PAG and yes- it lived up to its hype! Organized as part of the annual tech fest of IIT Roorkee, Cognizance, the event was hosted on CodeVillage, an online coding portal maintained jointly by <a href="https://www.facebook.com/SDSLabs">SDSLabs</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/sdspag">PAG</a>. </p>

<p>For the ones reading about it for the first time, Insomnia is an overnight programming contest held over 12 hours (9 pm IST - 9 am IST) . There are several questions of varying difficulty and each question carries one point (irrespective of difficulty). Ties are broken by the total time taken. Standard ACM-ICPC Rules. This year’s edition saw participation from over 170 teams from around the globe and over 1000 submissions made. If you compare these figures to an average contest hosted on codechef or spoj, they might not sound much to you, but considering the fact that the event was hosted on an independent platform (independent portal and independent grader) with less than half the publicity- we are ecstatic with the results! There were a few glitches we faced (mainly with the leaderboard), but the contest was smooth otherwise. Nevertheless we promise you that we’ll work them out before next year’s edition. </p>

<p>The overall winner of <a href="http://insomnia.cognizance.org.in/user/view_rank/1/10/27">Insomnia 2k14</a> was Mikhail Mayorov, a Russian guy(so no real surprises here!) who contested alone with the team name ‘SADBOYS’. Team ‘good_piggies’ stood second. Kudos to the members Manu Kashyap, Rishav Pati and Sandeep Mohanty! From IIT Roorkee, 4 teams managed a draw with 7 accepted solutions. Sorted on the basis of time, team ‘Invincibles’ came out at the top! Kudos to the members Rishabh Mor, Varun Syal and Yashpal Choudhary!</p>

<p>All the problems have been added on spoj for practice. The editorials for each have also been published and are available <a href="http://ge.tt/3FdSdNS1/v/0?c">here</a>.</p>

<p><em>Team Insomnia</em>: 
<img src="/images/posts/Insomnia/2k14.jpg"></p>

<p>As this post comes to an end, we’d like to say that we hope you guys enjoyed solving the problems as much as we enjoyed putting them up and we hope you’ll be back next year! For those of you who did not compete this year, we hope you’ll turn up next year and tell us what you think about it! We love to hear from you so if you have anything that you’d like to tell us- either about the contest problems, or about codevillage or about Putin taking over Crimea- we are all ears! For any sort of feedback, mail us at <a href="&#109;&#097;&#105;&#108;&#116;&#111;:&#112;&#097;&#103;&#105;&#105;&#116;&#114;&#064;&#103;&#109;&#097;&#105;&#108;&#046;&#099;&#111;&#109;">&#112;&#097;&#103;&#105;&#105;&#116;&#114;&#064;&#103;&#109;&#097;&#105;&#108;&#046;&#099;&#111;&#109;</a>.</p>

<p>Cheers!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ACM Qualifications 2013]]></title>
    <link href="http://pag.sdslabs.co/blog//2013/11/25/acm-qualifications-2013/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-25T22:20:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://pag.sdslabs.co/blog//2013/11/25/acm-qualifications-2013</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a long-awaited winter break comes closer catalyzing our recovery from the haunting memories of a badly screwed up end sem, it’s  good news for the geeks at IIT Roorkee coming after the online prelims of the ACM ICPC Indian Regionals. ACM ICPC is arguably the most reputed programming competition for college students across the world, and seeing Roorkee perform impressively at this huge scale makes us all really proud.</p>

<p>In India there are three sites which play host to the ACM ICPC Regionals: IIT Kanpur, IIT Kharagpur and Amritapuri. There have been a total of 14 qualifications from IIT Roorkee across the three sites this year, a new record in itself for the institute. In the regionals, which will be held around mid December, a total of about 600 teams from the very best technical institutes of the country and abroad shall be competing for their shot at a glorious opportunity of participating in the World Finals of the ACM ICPC. Every year the World Finals are held early July in Russia. This is a great achievement for the programmers and geeks alike at IIT Roorkee; and a record that we should strive to improve every year.</p>

<p>PAG congratulates all the teams that will be representing IIT Roorkee at the Regionals this year and wishes them the very best of luck as they gear up to take on the best in the business.</p>

<p>Here are the team and students from IIT Roorkee who have qualified for the ACM ICPC  Regionals 2013:</p>

<h3 id="amritapuri">Amritapuri</h3>

<ul>
  <li><strong>11coders</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Anubhav Bindlish† (CSE 2nd year)</li>
      <li>Aman Kumar Kedia† (CSE 2nd year)  	</li>
      <li>Kshitij Bathla† (CSE 2nd year)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>the-royal-flush</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Jaspreet Singh (CSE 4th year)</li>
      <li>Arpit Dua (MSP 5th year)	</li>
      <li>Sukun Tarachandani (EPE 4th year)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>frick-freak</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Ch. S Pramod (ECE 3rd year)</li>
      <li>R Shiva Tejesh (ECE 3rd year)</li>
      <li>Revanth Reddy (EE 3rd year)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>3Spades</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Adury Surya Kiran† (ECE 3rd year)</li>
      <li>Praneeth Reddy† (ECE 3rd year)</li>
      <li>Harsh Jhamtani† (CSE 4th year)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>tehloneclubs</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Vaibhav Gupta (CSE 4th year)</li>
      <li>Gaurav Singh   (CSE 4th year)</li>
      <li>Sushant Ojal (CSE 4th year)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>bapcoders</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Pankaj Gudlani (CSE 2nd year)</li>
      <li>Ankur Garg (CSE 2nd year)</li>
      <li>Bharat Gaind (CSE 2nd year)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>the-mathletes</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Aman Tripathi (EE 3rd year)</li>
      <li>Ankit Patel (CSE 3rd year)</li>
      <li>Saurabh Suman (ECE 3rd year)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>progenius</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Rajat Jain† (CSE 2nd year)</li>
      <li>Divij Bindlish (EE 2nd year)</li>
      <li>Vibhor Goel (EE 2nd year)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>hedylogos</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Saurabh Paliwal (CSE 4th year)</li>
      <li>Aayush Gupta (CSI 4th year)</li>
      <li>Siddharth Maheshwari (CSE 4th year)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>inquisitive</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Abhishek Kandoi†       	(CSE 2nd year)</li>
      <li>Priyanshu Sheth†        	(CSE 2nd year)</li>
      <li>Satyam Vijay†               	(CSE 2nd year)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>codewarrior</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Shubham Kansal†        	(CSE 3rd year)</li>
      <li>Shubham Mittal                   (MSM 5th year)           	</li>
      <li>Vishu Goyal                    	(CSE 3rd year)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="iit-kanpur">IIT Kanpur</h3>

<ul>
  <li><strong>3Spades</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Adury Surya Kiran†     	(ECE 3rd year)</li>
      <li>Praneeth Reddy†    	(ECE 3rd year)</li>
      <li>Harsh Jhamtani† (CSE 4th year)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>inquisitive</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Abhishek Kandoi†	(CSE 2nd year)</li>
      <li>Priyanshu Sheth†        	(CSE 2nd year)</li>
      <li>Satyam Vijay†               	(CSE 2nd year)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="iit-kharagpur">IIT Kharagpur</h3>

<ul>
  <li><strong>the-royal-flush</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Jaspreet Singh (CSE 4th year)</li>
      <li>Arpit Dua (MSP 5th year)</li>
      <li>Sukun Tarachandani (EPE 4th year)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><em>People marked with † are members of Programming and Algorithms Group</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to Programming]]></title>
    <link href="http://pag.sdslabs.co/blog//2013/07/30/welcome-to-programming/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-30T21:38:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://pag.sdslabs.co/blog//2013/07/30/welcome-to-programming</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Algorithm</strong>: <em>(Just)</em> A sequence of steps to get stuff done?</p>

<p>Technically, yes. Many of us have in fact been using algorithms for most part of our lives even without realizing that we are. Take for instance, when you want to look up a particular word in the dictionary. How long would it take you if the words were all arranged randomly with absolutely no relation? It is an algorithm in itself when you search for a given word, matching the leftmost letter of the word and keep moving right. That instance when you choose a particular path over another when looking for the fastest way to reach a friend’s house, you are technically solving a classic example of the Shortest Path Problem, a problem which could trouble the best programmers for hours!</p>

<p>However with the increasing dependence on computers and electronic gadgetry, you no longer need algorithms to get stuff done, but also need algorithms to guide machines do stuff for you. There is a mind-bogglingly huge amount of data present on the web and picking out a particular one is a task in itself. From the smallest chipsets to the multi-billion dollar spaceships circling the Earth to a random game of chess played on a summer afternoon, there are both complex and simple algorithms involved in everything.  </p>

<p>The study of efficiency in algorithm design is of huge importance. You don’t just need to consider <em>how to get something done</em>, you need to find a way <em>to get something done quickly</em>. Imagine if your GPS were to look for all ways to get from A to B, total their distances and then return the best route. Or if in a game of chess with a computer, the program were to try all possibilities and all possibilities arising out of those possibilities and all possibilities arising out of those and so on before it were to make an optimal move. You need to design algorithms that not only solve a given problem, but do so in a reasonable amount of time.</p>

<p>And the best part about algorithmic and logical problems is that once you start getting the hang of it, it becomes huge fun! You no longer need to take time out of your daily routine to practice (read: play) on online judges; it finds time for itself! So much so that it soon become a passion (and in some occasional cases an ‘addiction’) which you pursue not only because you want to end up with a high paying job at Facebook or Google, but because you enjoy doing it! </p>

<p><strong>How to start Programming?</strong></p>

<p>Am I good enough?</p>

<p>Yes you are, if you think you are not, think again! We say you can be. All you need is good logical and reasoning skills. If you have been a mathematics enthusiast in your school time, you already have the instinct in you.</p>

<p>Let’s introduce you to the amazing world of programming and algorithms.</p>

<p>Getting Started:</p>

<p>1.Pick any programming language(C, C++, Java, Python) whichever you feel 
comfortable with. Or if you don’t know any, you can easily learn C or C++ in hardly two weeks’ time. Only basics concepts are to be grasped.</p>

<p>Here are some useful references to help you:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/sdspag/549286215108068/">Schaum Programming with C++</a>: A very nice book to give you a quick introduction for C++</p>

<p><a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/56860240/C%2B%2B%20How%20to%20Program%2C%208th%20Edition.pdf">C++ How to Program, Deitel, 8th Edition</a>: For those who want more than just an introduction.</p>

<p><a href="http://ge.tt/9iw7sKn/v/0?c">Java How to Program, Deitel, 7th Edition</a>: For those who want to learn Java</p>

<p>2.Now that you have the tool, let’s use it to explore the algorithmic world</p>

<p>Here are some resources to make you familiar with the commonly used algorithms.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.coursera.org/course/algo">Coursera</a></p>

<p><a href="http://openclassroom.stanford.edu/MainFolder/CoursePage.php?course=IntroToAlgorithms">Stanford Open Class Room</a></p>

<p><a href="http://ocw.mit.edu/courses/electrical-engineering-and-computer-science/6-046j-introduction-to-algorithms-sma-5503-fall-2005/index.htm">MIT Open Courseware</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/sdspag/files/">CLRS</a> : The Bible for Algorithms</p>

<p>3.So here comes the most important phase of your coding journey. Practice. Practice more. Solve questions and keep exploring. And remember this:Frustration is normal. Don’t give up during this phase as your failure teaches you more than your success. Proceed gradually. The experience you gain here is worth your effort. Check these out</p>

<p><a href="http://www.spoj.com/">SPOJ</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.codechef.com/">Codechef</a></p>

<p><a href="http://projecteuler.net/about">Project Euler</a></p>

<p>4.If you wish to evaluate your progress, there are plenty of contests to keep you going. Apart from that, group contests prove very beneficial in improving your skills. You get to know your teammate’s approach (which may be better) too. </p>

<p>Participating in programming contests inculcates in you an urge to learn more and keeps you motivated.  You can find some ongoing contests here:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.codechef.com/">Codechef</a></p>

<p><a href="http://codeforces.com/">Codeforces</a></p>

<p>Also check out this <a href="http://www.quora.com/What-are-the-best-websites-a-programmer-should-visit/answer/Ashish-Gaur">answer</a> on quora for a more elaborate list. on quora for a more elaborate list.</p>

<p>Common <strong>Myths</strong> regarding Programming and Algorithms:</p>

<p>1.Programming is only for CS students.</p>

<p>Wrong! Here are the reasons:</p>

<p>You love maths, like solving puzzles and have an aptitude to do this, so you do it.Most of the CS companies like Microsoft, Facebook, Yahoo etc. are open for other branches too. If you are good enough in programming and algos then they will take you.</p>

<p>Even if you want to do higher studies, just try to explore what are the current research areas in your branch, you would find that most of them require programming - fields like Image processing, embedded systems, robotics, controls etc. Whichever field of engineering you are in , programming will help you somewhere.</p>

<p>2.You need to be an expert in a programming language to start with algorithms.</p>

<p>No, this opinion is completely wrong. You just need very basic knowledge of 
any language. They are just a tool, solving problems will automatically give you enough exposure to the language. An inquisitive mind and eagerness to learn is all that counts.</p>

<p><strong>Why PAG?</strong></p>

<p>With the huge influx of data in the ‘shared’ world; big-data, data mining, data extraction, data analysis, optimizations- these are topics that the coming generation of computer scientists needs to address. </p>

<p>Many of those computer scientists are now in college. Hopefully some of these world changers might be in India, and a few in IITR. PAG hopes to inculcate a feel for algorithms in these young engineers from the very beginning, get them acquainted with this field and help them realize why this fields bears importance in the real world. But then, why is solving problems on an online judge which thousands have already solved important?</p>

<p>Because a journey of a thousand miles begins from a single step. You cannot have a school boy who has just entered college and ask him to solve real life problems which legends have scratched their heads at. We need to start at the base and work our way up. Not only does practicing these problems helps develop one’s interest in algorithms, but at some level concepts like Dynamic Programming, Depth First Search and Graph Theory are what are extrapolated and applied in complex algorithms that boost the cores at Google or Facebook. To put it poetically, unless you know your ABCs you have no hope of finishing a novel. </p>

<p>And that is what PAG hopes to do. It hopes to help the students at R understand these concepts and why it is important for them to do so by bringing them together in a positive competitive environment.Coming together every week to share knowledge, we get to learn so much more than anyone of us individually ever could. Holding regular contests at R and annually on an international scale, keeps everyone motivated to keep doing better. It helps us to learn and strive harder to learn more. </p>

<p><strong>But then, why should you join PAG?</strong></p>

<p>You may be a Grade 2 coder at Topcoder or someone who had no clue about what programming is up till now. It doesn’t matter. As long as you are eager to learn and love working your way around logical and intellectually challenging problems, PAG is looking for you! Every year PAG recruits some of the finest and smartest individuals who come to R. It brings them together in a shared group. There are regular discussions on varied topics of interest, contests are organized and even participated in, and of 
course chapos are given and not to forget the trips we have!!! </p>

<p>Last year a team from PAG qualified for the ACM ICPC World Finals (which happens to be the BIGGEST contest of its kind with participation from over 120 countries) and stood first among all the Indian teams there (and 60th
 overall). We also have several teams who compete in the Regionals of the same contest every year. </p>

<p>And that is the best part about joining PAG! You get to meet so many awesome individuals who you otherwise might not. Bringing like-minded people together who share a common passion helps all of us to learn from each other and improve ourselves. </p>

<p><strong>Recruitment</strong></p>

<p>PAG will be recruiting soon. We are not expecting you to know programming as of now, so if you don’t, it isn’t really an issue. If you have a basic aptitude and the willingness to learn, you are good to go! To stay updated about out recruitment process and other activities, join our <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/sdspag/">Facebook group</a> and like our <a href="https://www.facebook.com/sdspag">facebook page</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
